<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>go on Max McDonnell</title>
    <link>https://maxmcd.com/tags/go/</link>
    <description>Recent content in go on Max McDonnell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 06:21:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://maxmcd.com/tags/go/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Go on Val Town</title>
      <link>https://maxmcd.com/posts/running-go-on-val-town/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 06:21:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxmcd.com/posts/running-go-on-val-town/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s go on a winding debugging adventure together. I thought I could get a Go HTTP handler running on Val Town and I thought it would be easy. Val Town is a social website to write and deploy Typescipt. Val Town doesn&amp;rsquo;t support Go, but it supports WASM. Can we make it all work!?
 If you want to skip all this and just run Go on Val Town you can follow the instructions here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bramble: A Purely Functional Build System and Package Manager</title>
      <link>https://maxmcd.com/posts/bramble/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2021 21:21:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxmcd.com/posts/bramble/</guid>
      <description>About a year and a half ago I decided to start working on a build system inspired by Nix called Bramble. Andrew Chambers had launched hermes and I was messing around with starlark-go a bit and it seemed like writing a Nix-inspired functional build system with Starlark would be a nice way to better understand how they work.
Bramble is no longer a test project, and has matured into something that I think has a few interesting ideas worth sharing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Star: Go but in Python?</title>
      <link>https://maxmcd.com/posts/star/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 22:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxmcd.com/posts/star/</guid>
      <description>tl:dr star is a python(ish) programming environment that lets you call Go library functions. click down to the repl if you&amp;rsquo;d just like to play around
Starlark is Google&amp;rsquo;s custom subset of Python that it uses as a configuration language with Bazel. I started looking into it a little because it has some interesting characteristics. It&amp;rsquo;s not turing complete (no unbounded loops), it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have classes or higher level abstractions, it&amp;rsquo;s also deterministic and is somewhat safe to run untrusted user input.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>