<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>go on Max McDonnell</title>
    <link>https://maxmcd.com/tags/go/</link>
    <description>Recent content in go on Max McDonnell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 01:29:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://maxmcd.com/tags/go/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s make a Nix/Guix</title>
      <link>https://maxmcd.com/posts/lets-make-a-nix-guix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 01:29:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxmcd.com/posts/lets-make-a-nix-guix/</guid>
      <description>Nix (and the more recently created GNU Guix) are functional package managers. I&amp;rsquo;ve used NixOS for some time now and have thoroughly enjoyed using it. I was inspired by Andrew Chamber&amp;rsquo;s recently launched hermes to try implementing a simple version of Nix using Go and Starlark.
A quick overview of Nix/Guix Nix and Guix are package managers that &amp;ldquo;utilize a purely functional deployment model where software is installed into unique directories generated through cryptographic hashes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Star: Go but in Python?</title>
      <link>https://maxmcd.com/posts/star/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 22:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxmcd.com/posts/star/</guid>
      <description>tl:dr star is a python(ish) programming environment that lets you call Go library functions. click down to the repl if you&amp;rsquo;d just like to play around
Starlark is Google&amp;rsquo;s custom subset of Python that it uses as a configuration language with Bazel. I started looking into it a little because it has some interesting characteristics. It&amp;rsquo;s not turing complete (no unbounded loops), it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have classes or higher level abstractions, it&amp;rsquo;s also deterministic and is somewhat safe to run untrusted user input.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>